Welcome back to AM Northwest.
Our first guest is a wealth of information
when it comes to vintage treasures.
Here to share one of his most recent
collections and share some helpful tips,
we welcome back
antique appraiser Gary Germer.
Great to see you again.
You too.
Thanks for having me back.
So it looks like we have a Japanese
influenced vintage treasure here.
Yeah, Japanese and Chinese influenced.
Okay, so Asian.
What I'm working on right now is a collection
of snuff bottles is what these are.
Explain what snuff is first of all.
Well, snuff, a lot of people see
these and they're not uncommon.
You'll see them and you have a little knob
that comes up and there's a little spoon.
So everybody thinks, oh, opium, cocaine.
What snuff is, is a ground tobacco.
These were never meant for drugs use.
These were for ground tobacco.
And you remember two, three hundred years
ago how it was cultural in Europe to snort
a little bit of snuff and
then they would sneeze.
It's the same sort of a thing.
Tobacco started in North
America, went to Europe.
And then eventually went to China.
But at the end of the 1600s in China, into
the Ming Dynasty, it became illegal to smoke.
They called it tobacco addiction.
And they eliminated it.
They didn't want anybody
having tobacco addiction.
And the punishment if you were
a tobacco addict was death.
They would kill you.
Get out!
Yeah, it was a capital crime.
Wow.
So people went to using snuff.
And snuff was okay because they used ground
tobacco with some herbs and they considered
it medicinal.
Okay.
So you had these little, now
you had medicine bottles.
Right.
That you take your little snort
and it would clear your sinuses.
And you put some in there.
Some under your tongue, which mostly
they did, their tongue or lip.
And that would give you a boost of energy.
Right.
So they considered it medicinal.
So you could do snuff,
couldn't smoke for 200 years.
Okay, point us some of the ones that you find
that are the most valuable maybe or that you
love.
Well, I'm kind of a geek.
I love all of them.
Okay.
But they come in all kinds of materials.
They come in different sizes.
This is the most typical size that you
see because it would fit in your pocket.
Right.
That makes sense.
You can take it with you.
So these are jade.
And it kind of shows the
different colors of jade.
Wow.
They have lavender and white and of
course different shades of green.
There's lavender jade.
Yeah.
It's just slightly pinkish lavender there.
Wow.
Porcelain and hand painted
porcelain ones here.
And then the front row here is all kinds
of minerals, different kinds of stones.
There's malachite and
amber and things like that.
Oh, I see the malachite.
Okay.
These are fascinating on the top here.
These are reverse painted.
Those are actually painted on the inside.
Okay.
And they would take a little
stick with a little brush.
You're kidding me.
And the artist would paint them.
How is that even possible?
I don't know.
I can't even paint the wall in a bedroom.
Wow.
Whether I'm getting something like that.
So they're fascinating.
And you judge them by how well they're made,
how well they're painted or how well they're
carved.
Right.
There's a lot of modern, like these
carved, these are glass, it's Peking glass.
A lot of them have been reproduced, but they
use them by a pressing method to press the
glass.
Whereas the old ones are all hand carved.
So they can be worth thousands of dollars,
but they were kind of a status symbol.
Like men collected them in China, a lot like
wealthy men today might collect expensive
watches or blank pens
or something like that.
This showed your culture and you had them
on display and you could take your little
bit of snuff and sneeze.
You said some of them
are extremely valuable.
Like what is the most valuable one here?
The most valuable one here,
I'm still studying these.
I just got them in.
These are all old.
These are all original ones.
I think this is a really good one that is
the yellow stone there that is, I believe
it's a type of a malachite, but it's carved
with a couple of little bugs right on it.
Yeah, that's incredible.
I think it's really well carved.
Wow.
And then this is a really good one.
This famil rose is the palette, but it's
all kinds of dragons flying around it.
That is amazing.
That's a good one.
And then you have some ivory ones, right?
They did them also in ivory.
You can find them in wood.
You can find them in.
Like a beetle nut kind of a thing.
It was a hard nut.
So it came in all kinds of things.
Ivory of course.
There's lots of different fun.
Ivory.
And this is about as tiny
as they get is this one.
And then they get bigger.
They didn't do really big
ones because the snuff clumps.
You know, it draws moisture
and then it turns into a rock.
And so you want it just
a little bit at a time.
You say that like I should know that.
Yeah, well, I mean.
It's like my sugar bowl.
You know, if you don't
use it, it clumps up.
I get it.
And so.
And this one to me, I feel
like I've seen these around.
I don't know if.
But I've definitely seen these around.
This is more jade.
These are jade and these
are different types of jade.
And this was kind of what the people who are
going to estate sales or if you are dealing
with some things like this at your
home and you want to use a jade.
There's a couple of quick tips and
this is the takeaway from this.
These are jade.
This is a jade.
These are just this is actually a
buckle, a belt buckle that's been carved.
No way.
Yeah.
That's a belt.
It would go around us through
the silk belt on a woman's robe.
Wow.
And then they would also use them
as decorations on other things.
Handle handles for mirrors
and things like that.
OK.
And then this is a soapstone.
And of course, this one
looks obviously duller.
It's going to be the jade is going
to be a lot tends to be more glossy.
Right.
And more wax like where this seems dull.
But the three things you're looking at.
Jade is really hard.
And soapstone.
It's very common to find is not.
And one of the things you
do is a quick scratch test.
You don't want to do this on the surface.
We're going to ruin anything.
This is a piece that's already broken.
So it's kind of.
So you can take something sharp where no
one's going to see it and you scratch it.
Yeah.
And see how easily that scratch.
Jade won't do that.
Oh, Jade's very hard.
Now, Jade is more expensive than
more valuable than soapstone.
Yeah.
Soapstone is easily carved.
Right.
So you'll find a lot of soapstone
when you're out at estate sales.
And a lot of times people think, well, I'm
going to go to the store and I'm going to
buy something after someone keeps expensive
soapstone for 20 bucks in New York address
sometimes and one of the other tells is
then you take your piece of jade and if
you can hold it in your hand jade
doesn't get warm it doesn't absorb heat
like glass would oh so you hold it
for a few for 30 seconds or 60 seconds
depending on how warm your hands yeah
and then I usually touch it to my face
and it still feels cool then that's Jay
that's it's probably jade and then the
other thing you're looking at is in
You can see the different
variations of color.
You can see by your eye.
But if you get into these other ones with
your magnifying glass, you'll also see some
variations of color.
So if it's hard, it won't scratch.
It's cold, it stays cold.
Chances are you have jade.
And then if you think it's a good piece,
then have it confirmed by a jeweler.
Awesome.
Thank you so much, Gary.
I appreciate that.
We'll put all the information about
you on our website at Cato.com.
Great, great information.
Thank you, Ellen.
All right.